Bubble sort bubble sort is a sorting algorithm that compares to adjacent elements and swap them until
no more swabs are needed, just like the movement of air bubbles in the water that rises up to the surface.
Each element of their array must move to the end in each iteration.
Therefore, it is called a bubble sort.
So consider this array.
It is unsorted array minus two, 54, zero 11 and minus nine.
We start at step zero by starting from the beginning of the array and the next one.
So we compared the first two elements minus two is greater than 50.
No, it's less than so the first iteration.
So the bubble sort is sorting algorithm.
As I told you, that compares to adjacent elements and swapped them until no more swaps are needed.
So the first step that iteration one is moving because we are minus two is less than 50 for.
OK, so we are.
Starting from the first index compared to the first and the second element, if the first element is
greater, then that second element, then they are swept.
Otherwise they remain the same.
Now compare to the second and the third element swept them if they are not in order.
OK.
And this process should be goes on until the last minute.
Fifty four is less than zero.
No.
So we need to swap that.
We remove them than this.
In this animation, we replace fifty four by zero and zero by fifty four.
And this is what happened in Pablo.
We are swapping them now.
We continue moving to the third and the fourth element.
The third element 54 is less than 11.
No.
So we need to swap them again.
This is the first step in the first, the second iteration.
54 replacing 11 and 11, 15 is replacing 54.
Now, in that third iteration, we moved to that last elements, the fourth and the fifth element.
So 54 is less than minus nine, no.
So we are going to swab that.
And this.
Manner.
OK, so we have reached the end of this array, so we go back to and move to this step number two,
so the first step is going through all the array, all the elements of the array and try to start swapping.
And we have swept that some elements.
Now we continue comparison to the first element and the second element of the array.
So minus two is less than zero.
It's OK.
So we move to the second one.
Zero is less than 11.
Yes.
So go and move to that next.
Couples Third Element and the Fourth Element 11 and minus nine 11 is less than minus nine.
No.
So go and swap them.
11 will be swapping them minus nine and minus nine will be replacing that in this position.
Now moving to the fifth, fourth and fifth, 11 and 34, and they are 11 is less than 54, so we have
done again, we go to the step number three by iterating, by starting from iteration, from the first
position.
OK, so every time we need to.
Until no more swaps are needed, so we always go back to the first until no more swaps are needed.
Minus two is less than zero.
Yes.
So we move to the second and the third zero is less than minus nine.
No.
So we need to swap them.
So minus nine is less than zero.
We are replacing them.
We move to the third and fourth.
Zero is less than 11.
Yes, 11 and less than 54.
Yes.
So again, go and go back to the first iterations, minus nine to the first element minus nine, as
is greater, then minus two.
No, minus nine shouldn't be swapped and minus two.
So here we swap minus two and minus nine.
The first element becomes minus nine, and we start comparing these elements to the end of that.
Minus two.
Less than zero.
Yes.
Zero.
Less than 11.
Yes.
Eleven less than fifty four.
So this way, we have activated through our array using bubble sort and we have swept the elements in
a way that they are sorted in an increasing order.
This is how bubble of algorithm work.
No, this is the idea.
This is that animation.
This is the visualization of this process.
Let's move into the algorithm and then see it how to implement it in C language and how to implement
it in an exercise in Java.
OK.
So bubbles sort algorithm.
It starts by bubbles, sort.
We should make bubbles for every element or method so that tucks into an array into an argument and
array.
OK, so this array that we are going to, that we are going to make it sort that we took it into the
parameter and the start from four.
We are going to make it for a loop that starts iterating through this.
Elam at this array from minus one I less than minus one index of the last unsorted element minus one.
So if that element left is less than or greater, then right.
So if we are going to sort it in increasing order, if the left element is greater than the right element,
then swipe left element and right element.
This is how the bubble sort works and bubble sort.
This is the algorithm after finishing all of this.
So we are going to enter a loop a for loop that starts from minus one to the index of the last unsorted
element minus one.
And we need to check if the left element is greater than the right element, then that's what what took
place and we need to swap the left and the right.
OK.
In next videos, we are going to see how to implement bubble sort algorithm in C and how to implement.